Guide to the John Hope Franklin papers, 1891-2010, bulk 1950-2010 RL.10029
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings (W), 1934-2009 and undated; 43 boxes
  - Articles, 1934-2007 and undated
    - "The Great Confrontation: The South and the Problem of Change,"Journal of Southern History (Vol. 38, no. 1), Feb. 1972 (Box W23)
    - "Negro, American," 1972 (Box W23)
    - "Negro Americans and Lyndon Johnson's Great Society," Focus, Feb. 1973 (Box W23)
    - "Looking to the Future with an Eye on The Past," Detroit News, Oct. 1973 (Box W23)
    - "The Historian and Public Policy Issues," First Regional American Studies Assn. Seminar of East Asia, July 1973 (Box W23)
    - "On the Oversupply of Graduate Students," Daedalus, Fall 1974 (Box W23)
    - "The American Scholar," Summer 1974 (Box W23)
    - "The Enforcement of the Civil Rights Act of 1875," Prologue, Fall 1974 (Box W23)
      Includes correspondence, 1975-1977.
    - "George Washington Williams," April 1975 (Box W23)
    - "The Moral Legacy of the Founding Fathers," University of Chicago Magazine, Summer 1975 (Box W23)
    - "Librarians in a Pluralistic Society," Annual Meeting of the American Library Assn., June 1975 (Box W23)
    - "The North, the South, and the American Revolution," Journal of American History (Vol. 62, no. 1), June 1975 (Box W23)
    - "Negro Americans in the Third Century of Independence," US News and World Report, 1976 (Box W23)
    - "Racial Equality in America: The Old Order Changeth Not," Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, Fall 1976 (Box W23)
    - "The Historian and Public Policy," The History Teacher, May 1978 (Box W23)
    - "George Washington Williams and the Beginnings of Afro-American History," Critical Inquiry, Summer 1978 (Box W23)
    - "Education of Black Americans," Change, October 1979 (Box W23)
    - "Mirror for Americans: A Century of Reconstruction History," American Historical Review (Vol. 85,no. 1), Feb. 1980 (Box W24)
    - Invoice for an article in a series on "Black Americans" commissioned by ICA American Embassy, Paris, August 8, 1980 (Box W24)
    - "A Visit to Sierra Leone and Senegal," March 3-21, 1981 (Box W24)
    - "The Land of Room Enough," Draft, Daedalus (Vol. 110, no. 2),Spring 1981 (Box W24)
    - "The Land of Room Enough," Spring 1981, 2 folders (Box W24)
    - "The Nineteen Eighties: Prologue and Prospect," with Kenneth Clark, Joint Center for Political Studies, 1981, 2 folders (Box W24)
      Includes 1979-1981 correspondence and drafts.
    - "Whither Afro-American History," Chicago Afro-American Teacher's Assn., 1981 (Box W24)
    - "Ongoing Fight for Indivisible Equality," Chicago Sun-Times, Feb. 1982 (Box W24)
    - "John R. Lynch, Republican Stalwart from Mississippi," Southern Black Leaders of the Reconstruction Era, ed. by Howard Rabinowitz,1980-1982 (Box W24)
    - "A Honorary Degree for a New Library: What Price a University's Independence?" The Chronicle of Higher Education, Jan. 27, 1982 (Box W24)
    - "George Washington Williams: The Massachusetts Years," 1983 (Box W24)
    - "A Policy Framework for Racial Justice," 1983 (Box W24)
    - "On Thinking About History," Duke University How to Think Straight Series, March 1984 (Box W24)
    - "A Modest Achievement," October 1984 (Box W24)
    - "Lincoln's Evolving View of Freedom," 1984-85 (Box W24)
    - "A Modest Imperialism," 1985 (Box W24)
    - "The Use and Misuse of the Lincoln Legacy," 1985 (Box W24)
    - "Effetti Sociali Delle Differenze..." 1986 (Box W24)
    - "Slavery and the Constitution," Encyclopedia of the American Constitution, 1986 (Box W24)
    - "On the Evolution of Scholarship in Afro-American History," in Darlene Clark Hine ed., The State of Afro-American History, 1986 (Box W24)
    - "Franklin Says Bork Could Reverse Racial Progress," Duke Dialogue, Oct. 2, 1987 (Box W24)
    - "The Desperate Need for Black Teachers: A Special Appeal," Change, May/June 1987 (Box W24)
      Includes 1977 correspondence from prior publication of same article.
    - "The Foundations From Which All Blessings Flow?" Scholarship Today, Library of Congress, 1987 (Box W24)
    - "Black Initiative and Government Responsibility," 1987 (Box W24)
    - "Washington's Shameful History of Racial Bigotry," The Washington Post, April 1988 (Box W24)
    - "Afro-American History: State of the Art," Journal of American History (Vol. 75, no. 1) June 1988 (Box W24)
    - "Duke Committed to Freedom of Speech," Durham Herald, August 22, 1988 (Box W24)
    - "The Land of Room Enough," Daedalus (Vol. 117, no. 3), Summer 1988 (Box W24)
    - "The Desperate Need for Black Teachers," March 1988 (Box W24)
    - "Opening the Door of Opportunity," Journal of the National Medical Association (Vol. 8, no. 12), 1988 (Box W24)
    - "Why Freedom Doesn't Mean Equality," Boston Globe, Feb. 26, 1989 (Box W24)
    - "Quasi-Free," Spring/Summer 1989 (Box W24)
    - "Reagan: Mean-Spirited, Vindictive, Negative," 1989? (Box W24)
    - "The Use and Misuse of the Lincoln Legacy," Illinois History (Vol. 43, no. 5), Feb. 1990 (Box W24)
    - "Their War and Mine," Journal of American History" (Vol. 77, no. 2), September 1990 (Box W24)
    - "W.E.B. DuBois: A Personal Memoir," Massachusetts Review (Vol. 31, no. 3), Autumn 1990 (Box W24)
    - "Who Divided This House?" Chicago History (Vol. 19, no. 3-4), Fall and Winter, 1990-91 (Box W38)
    - "Insult to Mandela," Durham Morning Herald, July 24, 1990 (Box W38)
    - "Taking Stock after a Hard Fight," News and Observer, Nov. 11, 1990 (Box W38)
    - "Runaway Slaves: Counting the Costs," American Visions, Feb. 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Franklin: War Protest Justified," Duke Dialogue, April 4, 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Traversing the Road to Race and History," Magazine of the Florida Endowment for the Humanities, Spring 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Booker T. Washington, Revisited," New York Times, Aug. 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Black War Critics Right," News and Observer (Raleigh), April 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Unequal Protections Under the Bill of Rights in the Early Days," The Key Reporter, Winter 1991-1992 (Box W38)
    - "On the Nomination of Judge Clarence Thomas to the U.S. Supreme Court," July 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Thomas: Our New Booker T. Washington," Daily News, August 8 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Illiberal Education: An Exchange," New York Review, September 26, 1991 (Box W38)
    - "Unequal Protection Under the Bill of Rights in the Early Days," The Key Reporter, Winter 1991-1992 (Box W38)
    - "The Emancipation Proclamation: An Act of Justice," Prologue:Quarterly of the National Archives (Vol. 25, no. 2), Summer 1993 (Box W38)
    - "The Responsibility is Ours," The Trumpet of Conscience (Vol. 8, no. 1), Dec. 1993 (Box W38)
    - "Vintage Years: The First Decade," on the occasion of receiving the 31st annual Cosmos Club Award, 1994 (Box W38)
    - "Three Great African American Women of Letters: Rita Dove, Maya Angelou, Toni Morrison," The Trumpet of Conscience (Vol. 8, no. 2), March 1994 (Box W38)
    - "From Progress to Poverty," The Trumpet of Conscience (Vol. 10, no. 5), Nov. 1994 (Box W38)
    - "The Movement, once it acquired mass, was irresistible," Forum: Magazine of the Florida Humanities Council, Winter 1994-1995 (Box W38)
    - "The South: Perspective for Tomorrow," American Issues Forum I, National Humanities Center, 1995 (Box W38)
    - "Lynch, John Roy, and Williams, George Washington," in American National Biography, 1995-1996 (Box W38)
    - "Tulsa's Race War," Tulsa County Historical Society, 1996? (Box W38)
    - "Acquiring a Jacob Lawrence Painting," Doubletake Magazine, 1996 (Box W38)
    - "Carter G. Woodson's Dream," The Journal of Blacks in Higher Education, Autumn 1997 (Box W38)
    - "An Opportunity and a Responsibility," Issues (Duke Endowment), Summer 1997 (Box W38)
    - "Paul Robeson: Icon for the Twenty-First Century," Emerge Magazine, 1998 (Box W38)
    - "The Journey to Checotah," U.S. Airways Attache, 1998 (Box W38)
    - "North Carolina: My Foster Home," in William Mangum's Carolina Preserves, 2000 (Box W38)
      Includes drafts and 1998-2002 correspondence.
    - "The Train from Here," Attache, US Airways, July 1998 (Box W38)
    - "George Washington Williams," American National Biography correspondence, 1999 (Box W38)
    - "The C. Eric Lincoln Papers: An Appreciation," 1993-1999 (Box W38)
      Includes related correspondence.
    - "The Meaning, Value of Education," Daily Oklahoman, Oct. 2000 (Box W38)
    - "If the Pursuit of Wealth Replaces Love of Learning, We Will Be All the Poorer," Winston-Salem Journal, Oct. 2000 (Box W38)
    - "The Legacy of Racism in America," 2001 (Box W38)
    - "Race in America: Looking Back, Looking Forward," American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Academy Bulletin, Fall 2001 (Box W38)
    - "George Washington Williams of Ohio," 2001 (Box W38)
    - "Horowitz's Diatribe Contains Historical Inaccuracies," The Chronicle, March 2001 (Box W38)
    - "Edward Franklin Frazier: A Memoir," University of Missouri Press, 2002 (Box W38)
    - "Biographical Sketch of Mollie Lee Parker Franklin," Uncrowned Queens Project, 2003 (Box W38)
    - "An Artistic Odyssey," Grant Hill Collection, Feb. 2003 (Box W38)
    - "The Road From Brown," 2004 (Box W38)
    - "John Hope Franklin: The Fisk Years," Journal of Blacks in Higher Education, Autumn 2005 (Box W38)
    - "The Quest for Freedom: Runaway Slaves and the Plantation South," Slavery, Resistance, and Freedom, Gettysburg Civil War Institute, 2007 (Box W38)
    - "African Americans and Africa," undated (Box W38)
    - "Buck Colbert Franklin, 1879-1960," short biography, undated (Box W38)
    - "Discovering a Pioneer," Journal of Negro History, undated (Box W38)
    - "Education for Democratic Living," undated (Box W38)
    - "Eric Williams and Howard University," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Face Behind the Veil," undated (Box W38)
    - "From Progress to Poverty," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Genesis of Segregation in the New South With Special Reference to Separate Schools for Negroes," undated (Box W38)
    - "Great Britain and the Emancipation Proclamation," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Growth of Negro Thought: 1865-1900," undated (Box W38)
    - "Higher Education and the Goals of Democracy," undated (Box W38)
    - "History: Handmaiden of the Law,"undated (Box W38)
    - "James G. Birney's Anti-Slavery Activities in Cincinnati, 1835-1837" undated (Box W38)
    - "Martin Luther King and the Afro-American Protest Tradition," undated (Box W38)
    - "My Position on War and Other Forms of Violence," undated (Box W38)
    - "Needed: A History of All the People and Needed: An UnAmerican Creed," both undated (Box W38)
    - "The Negro in America," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Negro in the Progressive Era," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Negro Social Scientist and the New American Revolution," undated (Box W38)
    - "Negro Thought in the 20th Century," undated (Box W38)
    - "The New America and the New Europe: A Scholar's Reflections," undated (Box W38)
    - "A New Birth of Freedom," undated (Box W38)
    - "A New Stability," undated (Box W38)
    - "A New Viewpoint in Negro History" (Box W38)
    - "A New Vision for America," undated (Box W38)
    - "An Open Letter to Mr. Jonathan Doe: Some Reflections on Racial Inequality in the United States," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Past in the Future of the South," undated (Box W38)
    - "Paternalism Before and After Emancipation," undated (Box W38)
    - "Patterns of Mass Migration: Policy and Population Pressures," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Politics and Strategies of the New Beginning," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Politics of Reconstruction," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Preservation of the Union" (Box W38)
    - "Race in America: A World Problem," undated (Box W38)
    - "Research in Southern History: Prelude to Understanding," undated (Box W38)
    - "The Salzburg Seminar in American Studies," undated (Box W38)
    - "School Broadcasting in Britain," undated (Box W38)
    - "Williams, George Washington," undated (Box W38)
    - "Writings Since World War II on Slavery," the Civil War, and Reconstruction, undated (Box W38)
    - Requests for reprints, 1973-1981 (Box W38)
  - Speeches, 1944-2006 and undated
    Includes drafts, outlines, published versions, and supplemental material from Franklin's speeches, dating from 1944 to 2006 and undated. Includes speeches given at schools, universities, meetings, conferences, and other events. Speeches are listed chronologically, except undated speeches, which are listed alphabetically at the end of the subseries.
    - "Youth Facing the World Today," Berry O'Kelly School, May 1944 (Box W38)
    - "An Adventure in Democracy," Jordan Sellars High School, Burlington North Carolina, May 1944 (Box W38)
    - "Our Educational Symbols," Fayetteville State Teacher's College, May 1944 (Box W38)
    - "Industry and Race Relations," July 1944 (Box W38)
    - "Scholarship in Wartime," North Carolina College for Negroes, 1944 (Box W38)
    - "The Negro in Post-War Readjustment: An Historical View," University of Michigan, 1945 (Box W38)
    - "Charles Lenox Redmond," The Doreas Club, Jan. 1946 (Box W38)
    - "The Making of Tomorrow," State Teacher's College of St. Louis, Feb. 1946 and Lincoln University, Feb. 1946 (Box W38)
    - "The Awakened South," 1949 (Box W38)
    - "Civil Rights Platform for Historians," St. James A. Mezirow Church, March 1949 (Box W38)
    - "The Negro in America," International Student Center, March 1949 (Box W38)
    - "Commencement address," Morris Brown College, Aug. 1949 (Box W38)
    - "Address to Alpha Kappa Delta," Fisk University, Jan. 1950 (Box W38)
    - "Stevens and Sumner: Radical Americans," D.C. Social Studies Teachers, Feb. 1950 (Box W38)
    - "The Honor of Being a Scholar," Dunbar High School, May 1950 (Box W38)
    - "Our Great Commitment," Phi Beta Kappa, Fisk University, April 1952 (Box W38)
    - "Civil Rights and Education of the American Negro," State Teacher's College, New York, May 1952 (Box W38)
    - "A Perspective for Youth Today," Eastern Regional Banquet, Pittsburgh, May 1952 (Box W38)
    - "Hoffman-Boston High School," Virginia, June 1952 (Box W38)
    - "Omicron Kappa Upsilon Dental Honor Society," June 1952 (Box W38)
    - "Fisk University," Presentation of the Phi Beta Kappa key, April 1953 (Box W38)
    - "A Bright New Tomorrow," Elizabeth City State Teacher's College, May 1954 (Box W38)
    - "A New Service for Negro History," outline, Hampton Institute, 1954 (Box W38)
    - "You Have Tomorrow," Armstrong Technical High School, Jan. 1955 (Box W39)
    - "Changing With the Times," Bluefield State College, Feb. 1955 (Box W39)
    - "In Search of a Tradition," Howard University, March 1955 (Box W39)
    - "M.I.T. National Intercollegiate Conference on Selectivity and Discrimination in American Universities," March 1955 (Box W39)
    - "Braunschweig Conference," Aug./Sept., 1955 (Box W39)
    - "Education for Wisdom," Springarn High School, Nov. 1955 (Box W39)
    - "BBC Broadcasts," Talks for Sixth Forms, Spring Term 1955 (Box W39)
    - "John Hope Franklin: The New Negro and the New Deal," Howard University Graduate School, 1955 (Box W39)
    - "Anti-Communism in America: The British View," 1955 (Box W39)
    - "Revolutions of Our Time," 75th anniversary of the founding of Spelman College, 1955 (Box W39)
    - "Your Reasonable Service," Sargent Presbyterian Church, March 1956 (Box W39)
    - "Uses of History for the Minister," Howard School of Religion, May 1956 (Box W39)
    - "Famous Folk of Color," Field Program Service, 1956 (Box W39)
    - "Europe and the American Race Problem," Hampton Institute, 1957 (Box W39)
    - "Lincoln and Public Morality," Chicago Historical Society, 1959 (Box W39)
      Reprinted in History, Oct. 1959. Includes related 1958-1959 correspondence.
    - "Booker T. Washington," The Man and the Educator, Tuskegee Institute, March 1959 (Box W39)
    - "The Battle Against Mediocrity," St. Paul's College, April 1959 (Box W39)
    - "Lincoln and the Politics of War," Broadcast Music, Inc., 1959 (Box W39)
    - "The Dilemma of Brotherhood in Modern America," Congregation Beth Emeth, Feb. 1960 (Box W39)
    - "To Educate All the Jeffersonians," Conference on the Gifted Negro Student, April 1960 (Box W39)
    - "Speech Before the South Carolina Senate," May 1960 (Box W39)
    - "Education and Social Responsibility," Morgan State University, June 1960 (Box W39)
    - "The Dilemma of the American Negro Scholar," Smith College, Dec. 1960 (Box W25)
    - "The Making of an Historian," University of Texas, Austin, 1960-1970 (Box W25)
    - "Problems of Freedom During the Civil War," New York University, Dec. 1960 (Box W25)
      Outline.
    - "Problems of Freedom During the Civil War," New York University, Dec. 1960 (Box W25)
    - "The Modern Role of the Liberal Arts College," North Carolina College, 1960 (Box W25)
    - "Working for Democracy in the United States and Africa," Detroit, Feb. 1961 (Box W25)
    - "A Victory More Certain," Feb., 1961 (Box W25)
      On the occasion of Carl Haverlin receiving the Lincoln Award.
    - "Federal Enforcement of Civil Rights," Sidney Hillman Lecture Series, Howard University, Dec. 1961, 3 folders (Box W25)
    - "Address delivered at Bennett College," March 1961 (Box W25)
    - "United Negro College Fund Meeting," Dalton School, Jan. 1961 (Box W25)
    - "In the Steps of the Founders," Barber-Scotia College, 1961 (Box W25)
    - "Democracy's Quest for Fulfillment," Brooklyn Academy, May 1962 (Box W25)
    - "The Changing Role of the Negro Citizen in 20th Century America," Amerika-Haus Koln, Aug. 1963 (Box W25)
    - "The Dignity of Man: Perspectives for Tomorrow," National Council for the Social Studies, Los Angeles, Nov. 1963 (Box W25)
    - "A People's Travail: A Personal Testament," 1963 (Box W25)
    - "Commencement Address," Bennett College, May 1964 (Box W25)
    - "Choose Ye This Day! Long Island University," June 1964 (Box W25)
    - "In the Image of Greatness," Springarn Medal Presentation to Roy Wilkins, June 1964 (Box W25)
    - "Early Civil Rights Movement: A Midcentury Inventory," July 1964 (Box W25)
    - "The Douglass Years," Pepsi-Cola General Bottlers, Inc., Chicago, Dec. 1964 (Box W25)
    - "Indo-American Cultural and Educational Exchange: Some New Perspectives," Hyderabad, 1964 (Box W25)
    - "The Freedom to Dissent," University of Rochester, Feb. 1965 (Box W25)
    - "Perspectives on Protest: Two Centuries in the Negro Appeal for Justice and Reason," Rockford College, March 1965 (Box W25)
    - "New Frontiers of Freedom," Hamline University, June 1965 (Box W25)
    - "New Frontiers of Freedom," Brooklyn College, June 1965 (Box W25)
    - "History as Literature: A Humanistic Approach to the Past," Indiana University, July 1965 (Box W25)
    - "Equality for All Americans: Roadblocks in the Fulfillment of the American Dream," University of California, Riverside, July 1965 (Box W25)
    - "Abraham Lincoln and Civil Rights," Gettysburg National Cemetery, Nov. 1965 (Box W25)
    - "Abraham Lincoln and Reconstruction," Gettysburg College, Nov. 1965 (Box W25)
    - "In the Cause of Service and Excellence," Philadelphia, Feb. 1966 (Box W25)
    - "More Stately Mansions for Learning," Fred J. Carnage Junior High School, Raleigh, North Carolina, March 1966 (Box W25)
    - "The Negro American's Interest in Africa: A Historical Overview," Roosevelt University, May 1966 (Box W25)
    - "The New International Community: An Educational Exchange," May 1966 (Box W25)
    - "Freedom from Confusion and Despair," Radcliffe College, June 1966 (Box W25)
    - "The Many Faces of Negro History," Frank London Brown Club, Feb. 1966 (Box W25)
    - "A Century of Honor," Jubilee Day, Fisk University, Oct. 1966 (Box W25)
    - "The New American History: Problems and Obstacles," Woodson Memorial Luncheon, Oct. 1966 (Box W25)
    - "The Negro Since Freedom," Vann Woodward Lecture Series, Nov. 1966 (Box W25)
    - "Two Centuries in the Struggle for Freedom and Equality," Albion College, Jan. 1967 (Box W25)
    - "Universal Education: The Quest for Equality in America," Cleveland, Jan. 1967 (Box W25)
    - "Frederick Douglass," Seventy Years Later, Feb. 1967 (Box W25)
    - "The Negro Since Freedom," Washington D.C., 1967 (Box W25)
      In Voice of America, organized by C. Vann Woodward. Includes correspondence and brochures.
    - "The Higher Learning and the Higher Law," San Jose State College, May 1967 (Box W25)
    - "A Perspective for the Future," Rhode Island State College, June 1967 (Box W25)
    - "The Higher Learning and the Higher Law," Illinois State University, September 1967 (Box W25)
    - "Washington and the Post-Reconstruction South," Southern Historical Association, Nov. 1967 (Box W25)
    - "Roots of Alienation," National Commission on Civil Disorders, 1967(?) (Box W25)
    - "Education at High Tide," Tribute to Harry D. Gideonse, Feb. 1968 (Box W25)
    - "Discussion of the Papers by Professors Abraham Blaustein and Rudwick," Organization of American Historians, April 1968 (Box W25)
    - "Commencement Speech," Johnson C. Smith University, May 1968 (Box W25)
    - "Martin Luther King and American Traditions," April 1969 (Box W25)
    - "The Future of Negro American History," New School for Social Research, April 1969 (Box W25)
    - "The Negro as Politician During Reconstruction: The Case of John R. Lynch," Wayne State University, May 1969 (Box W25)
    - "In the Cause of Freedom," Arizona State University, June 1969 (Box W25)
    - "In the Cause of Freedom," Hampton Institute, June 1969 (Box W25)
    - "In the Cause of Freedom," Kalamazoo College, June 1969 (Box W25)
    - "The Heritage of All Men," U.S. Information Agency, Cultural Services Branch (Box W25)
    - "George Washington Williams and Africa," Webster College, Dec. 1970 (Box W25)
    - "Ethnicity in American Life: The Historical Perspective," Loyola University, Dec. 1969 (Box W26)
    - "Ethnicity in American Life: The Historical Perspective," Norfolk State College, Jan. 1970 (Box W26)
      Includes 1971 correspondence about the publication of the speech.
    - "Ethnicity in American Life: The Historical Perspective," Oakland University, January 1970 (Box W26)
    - "George Washington Williams and Africa," May 1970 (Box W26)
    - "Building Tomorrow's World," University of Chicago High School, 1969 (Box W26)
    - "Building Tomorrow's World," Southeastern High School, Detroit, 1970 (Box W26)
    - "Focusing on International Relations," Chicago International Program, September 1971 (Box W26)
    - "Introduction of Speaker," Carter G. Woodson Commemorative Program, ASALH, Oct. 1971 (Box W26)
    - "Charles Harris Wesley," Washington D.C., Oct. 1971 (Box W26)
    - "Carter G. Woodson," Builder of Monuments, Washington D.C., Oct. 1971 (Box W26)
    - "Introduction of John Hope Franklin at the Annual Dinner of the Southern Historical Association," Houston, Nov. 1971 (Box W26)
    - "The Great Confrontation: The South and the Problem of Change," Southern Historical Association, Houston, Nov. 1971 (Box W26)
    - "The Scholar-Teacher in the University," University of Chicago Trustees Dinner for the Faculty, Jan. 1972 (Box W26)
    - "The Americanization of George Washington Williams," Cornell University, April 1972 (Box W26)
    - "Healing the Nation's Scars," University of Tulsa, May 1972 (Box W26)
    - "A Good Name," Dedication of the E. Franklin Frazier School, Chicago, June 1972 (Box W26)
    - "W.E.B. DuBois," Historian of the Reconstruction, University of Iowa (Box W26)
      Includes 1973 correspondence.
    - "The Historian and Public Policy Issues," Washington D.C., Nov. 1972 (Box W26)
    - "Learning in Yankee Land," Walter Lynwood Fleming Lectures, April 1973 (Box W26)
    - "Southerners on the Grand Tour," Walter Lynwood Fleming Lectures, April 1973 (Box W26)